Keith Temple Cartoons
Keith Temple Cartoons
1961-1967
Temple, Keith.
5 linear ft.
180 original editorial cartoons and five scrapbooks of clippings of Temple's editorial cartoons published in the New Orleans Times-Picayune.
2649265
Biographical History
Keith Temple (1899-1980) was an Australian-American editorial cartoonist who worked for the New Orleans Times-Picayune for over 40 years.
Born in Australia in 1899, Temple volunteered at age 17 to serve with the Australian Imperial Forces during World War I. Temple’s brother was killed in the war and Temple himself was wounded. After his discharge, Temple decided to travel around the world. While visiting the United States in 1919, Temple ended up in a New Orleans hospital due to complications from his World War I wound. After his release from this costly hospital stay, Temple had to seek work and was hired as a reporter and news artist with the Times-Picayune. Temple left to spend one year with the New Orleans Item until he returned to the Times-Picayune as their editorial cartoonist. His first editorial cartoon with the paper appeared on May 23, 1923.
While an editorial cartoonist, Temple studied painting and sculpture at the New Orleans Arts and Crafts Club. Prompted by a libel suit at the newspaper involving one of his editorial cartoons, he also studied law at Loyola University, receiving a degree in 1927. Temple received a George Washington Honor Medal from the Freedoms Foundation in 1966. Temple retired from the Times-Picayune in 1967 and was replaced by Eldon Pletcher. Following retirement, Temple pursued painting, often creating works focused on New Orleans history drawn from his memories of New Orleans from the time following his arrival there and sketches he had made at the time.
Keith Temple died in Missisippi in 1980.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Keith Temple Cartoons contain original editorial cartoons and scrapbooks of clippings of his cartoons published in the New Orleans Times-Picayune.
Cartoons (1961-1967) contains artwork for 187 original editorial cartoons.
Dates typicaly are written in pencil at the bottom of the item; however many cartoons have additional dates written in pen directly below the image. The handwriting of these two dates differs. The date in pencil is likely from Temple or someone else at the newspaper. The source of the other date is unknown. It should be noted that the majority of cartoons list dates in the form of a day of the week and dates for the month and day and sometimes a year. However, when the months and days of the week are checked against a calendar, the years are often incorrect. Correct years have been estimated, noted in pencil on the back of the cartoons within brackets and when possible verified against the scrapbooks containing clippings of published cartoons. The collection also includes ten cartoons that lack complete dates; many of these are likely from 1961.
This particular collection of Temple's work contains cartoons about national and international events with little mention of state and local affairs. Many of Temple's cartoons depict concepts and ongoing issues such as opposed to specific events. For example, Temple explores the world's successes in science and the failure to solve social problems, poverty and population increases. Temple's work frequently focuses on peace. In an article in the January 19, 1969 issue of the Times-Picayune's Sunday magazine, Dixie Roto, Temple remarked, "I suppose I’ve drawn more cartoons in favor of the various peace conferences, disarmament plans and hopes than any other cartoonist in the land." Other prominent topics include auto safety, the failure of the Soviet Union to pay its United Nations' dues, voting requirements, and the effort to have commercial airline flights to Russia. Of particular interest is a cartoon mourning the end of the New York Herald Tribune newspaper, cartoons commemorating the 20th anniverary of the United Nations and a 1962 cartoon about Puerto Rico and statehood.
In addition to labels for specific places, people and concepts, Temple also included longer written statements about particular issues such as in a cartoon about civil rights and racial violence that contains the argument "violence creating more violence- adding to racial problems." Aside from Nikita Khruschev, Ho Chi Minh and Mao, political figures are largely absent from this particular collection of Temple's work. The United States is often represented by an Uncle Sam character while Temple anthropomorphizes both the world and nuclear weapons.
Overall dimensions for each piece are 15" x 20" with image sizes of approximately 12 1/2" x 15 1/2". Works were drawn in ink and crayon on Hi Art brand medium weight illustration board. Dates, notes and some captions appear in pencil.
The Scrapbooks (1965-1967) series is comprised of five scrapbooks of Temple's editorial cartoons published in the New Orleans Times-Picayune. Also there are occasionally other brief clippings about Temple included in the scrapbooks.
Arrangement of the Collection
Original artwork is arranged in chronological order, with one folder of cartoons for which dates were not determined appearing at the end of the collection.
Related Material
has collections of over one hundred cartoonists. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Temple, Keith -- Archives.; Ho Chi Minh, 1890-1969 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Khrushchev, Nikita Sergeevich, 1894-1971 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- ) -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Democratic Party (U.S.) -- Caricatures and cartoons.; United States. Congress. -- Caricatures and cartoons.; United Nations -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Times-picayune.; Art -- Cartoonists; American wit and humor, Pictorial.; Caricatures and cartoons -- United States.; Automobile industry and trade -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Civil rights movements -- United States -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Science -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Cold War -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Cartoonists -- United States.; Cartoonists -- Louisiana -- New Orleans.; Editorial cartoons -- United States.; Editorial cartoons -- Louisiana -- New Orleans.; World politics -- 1945-1989 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Nuclear weapons -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Peace -- Caricatures and cartoons.; United States -- Politics and government -- 1961-1963 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; United States -- Politics and government -- 1963-1969 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Cartoons (humorous images); Scrapbooks.; Clippings (information artifacts); Editorial cartoons.; Cartoonists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Original cartoons, gift of Keith Temple, 1967. Scrapbooks, gift of Howard-Tilton Memorial Library at Tulane University, 1976.
Inventory
- Cartoons, Click here for a detailed inventory.; See below for an index to the cartoons.
  - 1961 Apr, 1961 Jun-Jul (Oversize 1, Folder 1)
  - 1961 Aug-Sep (Oversize 1, Folder 2)
  - 1962 Jun-Aug (Oversize 1, Folder 3)
  - 1962 Sep-Oct (Oversize 2, Folder 1)
  - 1962 Nov-Dec (Oversize 2, Folder 2)
  - 1963 May, 1963 Jul-Sep (Oversize 2, Folder 3)
  - 1963 Oct-Dec (Oversize 2, Folder 4)
  - 1964 Jan-Feb, 1964 May, 1964 Jul-Aug, 1964 Oct-Dec (Oversize 3, Folder 1)
  - 1965 Feb-Mar (Oversize 3, Folder 2)
  - 1965 Apr-Jun (Oversize 3, Folder 3)
  - 1965 Jul (Oversize 4, Folder 1)
  - 1965 Aug, 1965 Nov-Dec (Oversize 4, Folder 2)
  - 1966 Jan-Mar (Oversize 4, Folder 3)
  - 1966 Apr-Jun (Oversize 4, Folder 4)
  - 1966 Jul-Aug (Oversize 5, Folder 1)
  - 1966 Sep (Oversize 5, Folder 2)
  - 1966 Oct-Dec (Oversize 5, Folder 3)
  - 1967 Jan (Oversize 5, Folder 4)
  - Undated, circa 1961 (Oversize 7, Folder 1)
- Scrapbooks
  - 1965 Jan-1967 Jan, 5 items (Oversize 6)
Index to cartoons
The following is a list of predominant people, places and subjects appearing in the editorial cartoons in this collection. The list is not exhaustive. Some subjects may require you to browse with alternative terms.
B= Box, F= Folder. For example: B1F1= Box 1 Folder 1.
Adenauer, Konrad B1F1-B1F2 B2F4
Africa B5F3
airline industry B1F2 B2F4 B5F3
Albania B3F2
Alliance for Progress B1F1-B1F2
American Bar Association B2F3
American Indians B4F3
anti-trust laws B3F2
armed forces B3F1 B4F2 B5F3
Asia B5F3-B5F4
auto industry B4F1 B4F3-B5F1 B7F1
automation B2F4 B3F2 B5F2
Belgium B1F3 B2F2
Berlin B1F1-B1F2 B2F1 B2F4 B7F1
Black Power B5F1
Britain B4F4
Buddhists B4F4
business B1F1
Castro, Fidel B2F1-B2F2 B3F1
Central Treaty Organization (CENTO) B3F1
China B1F3-B2F2 B3F1-B3F3 B4F3-B5F2 B7F1
civil rights B2F3-B3F1 B4F4-B5F2
communism B1F1 B2F1 B3F1-B5F3
Congo B1F3 B2F2
Congress B1F1 B1F3 B2F3 B3F1 B5F1 B7F1
construction industry B5F1
consumers B5F3
crime B5F3
Cuba B2F1-B2F2 B2F4
de Gaulle, Charles B3F1 B4F3-B4F4 B5F3
democracy B5F2
Democratic Party B2F1 B2F4 B3F3-B4F3
demonstrations B4F3
desegregation B3F3
Diem, Ngo Dinh B2F4
disarmament B1F1 B1F3 B4F1
Dominican Republic B3F3
draft B4F2
education B3F3 B5F2
Eichmann, Adolf B1F1
elections B2F1-B2F2 B5F2-B5F3
Erhard, Ludwig B2F4
espionage B5F3
Europe B5F1 B5F3
farming B1F3
foreign aid B3F2 B4F3 B5F2
Formosa B1F3
France B2F1
free enterprise B5F2
Freedom of Information Act B5F1
Gandhi, Indira B4F3
Germany B1F1-B1F2 B2F4 B7F1
Goldwater, Barry B3F3
Great Society B4F1 B4F3 B5F3
Gromyko, Andrei B4F4
Hammarskjold, Dag B1F2
Ho Chi Minh B3F2 B4F1-B4F2 B4F4-B5F1 B5F3-B5F4
holidays B2F3-B3F1 B4F1-B4F2 B4F4 B5F3-B5F4
Hoover, J. Edgar B5F3
House Un-American Activities Committee B4F2
housing B5F1-B5F2
hunger B5F3
India B2F2 B3F3 B4F3 B5F3
Indonesia B3F3 B5F2
industry (general) B2F1 B4F3 B7F1
inflation B4F4-B5F2
Israel B1F1 B5F3
Johnson, Lyndon Baines B3F3 B4F3 B5F2-B5F3
journalism B5F1
Kai-shek, Chiang B1F3
Kennedy, John F. B1F1 B2F1 B5F3
Kennedy, Robert F. B5F3
Khrushchev, Nikita B1F1-B2F2 B2F4
Korea B1F1
Kosygin, Alexey B3F2 B4F3
Ku Klux Klan B4F2-B4F3 B7F1
Ky, Nguyen Cao B4F4
Latin America B1F1-B1F2 B3F1 B7F1
liberty B2F3
literacy B4F3 B5F1
Louisiana B3F1
Malaysia B5F1
Malik, Adam B5F2
Mansfield, Mike B4F1
Marxism B3F1
Middle East B2F2 B5F3
minimum wage B5F2
Monroe Doctrine B2F1
Moynihan Report B5F2
NATO B2F1 B3F1
Nehru, Jawaharlal B2F2
New Orleans B2F2 B7F1
New York City B4F3 B5F1
Nhu, Madame Ngo Dinh B2F4
nuclear weapons B1F1-B2F2 B2F4-B3F1 B3F3 B4F2 B5F2
Organization of American States B3F1 B3F3
Pakistan B3F3 B4F3
Panama Canal B3F1
peace B1F1-B1F2 B2F1 B2F4-B4F1 B4F3-B5F2
Peace Corps B5F1
Philippines B5F1
Pope Paul VI B4F4
population B3F3 B4F3 B5F3
Puerto Rico B1F3
railroad industry B2F3-B2F4
religion B4F4
Republican Party B2F1 B2F4 B3F3-B4F4 B5F2
Russia B2F1-B2F2 B2F4 B4F3
science B2F1 B2F4-B4F1 B5F3
secrecy B3F3
shipping industry B1F3 B7F1
socialism B3F3
Southeast Asia Treaty Organization (SEATO) B3F1
Soviet Union B1F1-B2F1 B2F4-B4F1 B4F4-B5F1 B5F3 B7F1
space exploration B1F1 B1F3 B3F1-B3F2 B4F1 B4F3-B4F4 B5F3 B7F1
state and local governments B3F3 B5F3
Stikker, Dirk B2F1
stock market B4F1
strikes B1F3 B2F3 B3F2 B5F2
Sukarno B3F3 B5F2
Supreme Court B4F4
taxes B1F1-B2F2 B5F2
terrorism B5F2
Thailand B5F1
Thant, U. B2F1 B4F4
trade B2F4-B3F1 B7F1
traffic fatalities B4F1 B4F4
transportation B5F2
U.S. Constititution B3F2
unemployment B2F4
unions B3F2 B5F1 B7F1
United Nations B1F2 B2F1-B2F2 B3F1-B3F3 B4F3 B5F2-B5F3 B7F1
urban problems B5F2-B5F3
urban problems B5F2-B5F3
Vatican B4F4
Vietnam War B2F1 B3F1-B5F3
violence B2F3 B5F1
voting B3F2 B5F1-B5F2
war B2F1-B2F2 B4F2
War on Poverty B3F1
Warren Commission B5F3
Zedong, Mao B1F1 B1F3-B2F1 B3F2 B4F1-B4F2 B4F4-B5F4